ありがとうございます　ヒナタ様。
Thank you, Lady Hinata.
申し訳ありません。
I appreciate you treating my wound
when you're injured as well.
ヒナタ様こそ
おケガをされているのに…。
（ヒナタ）大丈夫。　私なら
ちゃんと治療してもらったから。
It's all right.
Someone has already tended
to my wounds.
今は　里の人手が足りないとき。
The village is
short-handed right now.
サクラさんも忙しそうだし
このくらいは　私が。
Sakura is so busy.
This is the least I can do.
（木ノ葉丸）ネジの兄ちゃん。
Neji!
（ウドン）あのね…　僕たちの取材に
協力してほしいんだ。
Can we interview you?
（ネジ）取材？
Interview?
（モエギ）ほら
この戦いで　ナルト兄ちゃんが→
Naruto played a huge part
in this battle, right?
すごく活躍したでしょう？
（木ノ葉丸）アカデミーの後輩たちに
頼まれちゃってさ。
And the younger kids at the Academy
asked us to do a spread
ナルト兄ちゃんの活躍をまとめた→
in the Academy newspaper
about his achievements.
学級新聞を作ることになったんだ。
で　みんなに
インタビューしてるってわけ。
So we're going around
interviewing everyone.
悪いが　他を当たってくれ。
Sorry, but ask someone else.
え～っ…　冷たいよ　ネジさん。
That's mean, Neji!
そうよ。　かわいい後輩たちが
楽しみにしてるんだから！
I'll say! The kids at the Academy
are looking forward to it.
頼むぞ　これ！
Please!
なあ　このとおり！
We're beggin' you!
しかたない。　では
とっておきの話をしてやろう。
Oh, fine. Then let me tell you
a very special story.
ano suiheisen ga touzakatte iku
Far beyond the horizon it continues
ao sugita sora ni wa ashita sura egake nakute
A sky so blue, you can't draw tomorrow
iki mo dekinai kurai yodonda hito no mure
It's stifling with crowds of people down here
boku wa itsukara koko ni moguri kondan da?
Just when did I dive into this?
kanashimi nante hakidashite mae dake mi tereba iin dakke?
Spit out sadness and keep looking ahead, right?
sore ja totemo matomo de irarenai
You can't stay true to yourself like that
subete o boku ga teki ni mawashite mo
Even if I turn against everything,
hikari o kasuka ni kanji terun da
I still feel glimmers of light
soko made yuke sou nara
If I could only reach it...
iki o shitakute koko wa kurushikute
I want to breathe, I'm suffocating here
yami o miageru dake no boku ja
Only looking up into the dark means,
ukabu houhou mo nai daibaa
I'm a diver who can't surface
iki o shite mite
Take a deep breath
tada no shiawase ni kizuitara mou nidoto oborenai yo
Discover joy, plain and simple and you'll never drown
- Leaf's History -
Neji Chronicles
あれは
約３年前→
It was roughly three years ago.
中忍試験　本選の日のことだ。
The day the final round of
the Chunin Exam took place.
俺たちが初めて参加した
あの年の中忍試験は→
Our first Chunin Exam that year
was met with many troubles.
いわくつきだった。
各国の大名など
多くの他国の人々が→
Feudal Lords and guests from
other nations all gathered
中忍試験を見るため
木ノ葉に入り込んでいる中…。
to watch the final round in the Hidden
Leaf Village, and in the midst of that,
＜ネジ：木ノ葉に恨みを持つ
抜け忍　大蛇丸が→
we received reports that a Rogue Ninja
named Orochimaru was after Sasuke.
サスケを狙っているとの情報があり→
不測の事態に備えて　里の各所には
厳重な警備網が敷かれていた。
The village took steps for
every contingency in every area
and security was
extremely tight.
本選の途中で　砂と音による→
During the finals, the Hidden Sand
and Hidden Sound conspired
木ノ葉崩しが
起こることになるが→
to destroy the Hidden Leaf.
この時点で
それを予測できる者など→
Something no one could
ever have predicted.
いるはずもなく→
各国から集まった観客が
熱狂的に見守る中→
Not yet knowing what was about to occur,
the matches continued,
and spectators from various nations
watched with intense interest.
試合は進められていた＞
＜　その頃　第１試合で
ナルトに敗北した俺は医務室にいた＞
Around that time, I was being
treated in the medical room,
having lost to Naruto
during the first match.
（テンテン）様子を見にきたわよ。
具合は　どう？
I came to see how you are.
How do you feel?
ああ　問題ない。
I'm fine.
気を落とすことないわ。
ナルトが勝つなんて　まぐれだもん。
Don't be disappointed.
It's sheer luck that Naruto won!
I'm sure you'll win the next-
次は　絶対…。
いや　それは　いいんだ。
Oh, I'm over that.
えっ…。
Huh?
少し前に　ヒアシ様がいらした。
Lord Hiashi came by
a little while ago.
俺たち分家は　命が尽き→
I had always believed that we members
of the branch family would never be truly free
この呪印が　白眼の能力を
封印して消えるときまで→
until the power of the Byakugan is sealed
away and our Curse Marks disappear.
自由になるものなどない。
そう思ってきた。
だが　父は違ったようだ。
But it seems Father thought
of it differently.
あがいても
変わらないものは　確かにある。
It's true that some things
cannot be changed.
しかし　俺は　すべてを→
But perhaps, I have been making
blind assumptions about everything.
決めつけすぎて
いたのかもしれないな。
ネジ…。
Neji...
ねぇ　会場に戻らない？
ガイ先生とリーも来たし→
Let's go back to the stadium.
Guy Sensei and Lee are here
うちはの試合
すごく　おもしろそうよ。
and the Uchiha's match looks
really exciting.
そうだな。
You're right.
＜　ちょうど　そのときのことだ＞
Then it happened.
＜大蛇丸の木ノ葉崩しが
始まったのだ＞
Orochimaru's destruction of
the Hidden Leaf had begun.
何なの？　あれ…。
What is that?!
気づいたか？　会場からの歓声が
途絶えている。
Have you noticed?
The cheering in the stadium has stopped.
ええ　空気が変わったみたい。
Yeah. Something in the air
is different.
白眼！
Byakugan!
＜大蛇丸率いる音
そして同盟国　砂の裏切りにより→
Due to the treachery
of Orochimaru's Hidden Sound
and his allies from the Sand,
our village was thrown into chaos.
里は　あっという間に
混乱の坩堝と化した＞
なんてことだ…。
How could this happen?!
里中のいたるところで
戦闘が起きている。
Fighting has broken out in
every corner of the village.
砂と音の忍たちが
木ノ葉に対して…。
Sand and Sound Ninja
against the Leaf.
それじゃ　まるで！
It's like...
ああ　戦争だ！
I know. It's like a war.
＜俺たちは　詳しい状況を
把握するため会場へと走った。
We rushed to the stadium to
find out just what was going on.
だが　このとき
すでに事件は始まっていたのだ＞
But unbeknownst to us, another incident
was already taking place.
あれは！
Is that...
長老様！
うっ…。
Elder!
ちょっと大丈夫！？
Hey, are you okay?!
（キバ）俺は…。
What happened to me?
＜　あとで聞いた話だが
キバは　この少し前→
Kiba later told us that he was knocked
unconscious by enemy ninja
中忍試験の後遺症で倒れた
ヒナタ様を介抱している際→
disguised as Anbu Black Ops,
while watching over Lady Hinata,
暗部に化けた敵に
倒されたらしい＞
who had collapsed due to
injuries from her previous match.
おい…　何なんだよ　これ！？
Hey... What the hell's
going on here?
（テンテン）どうやら
アンタは無事みたいね。
It seems you're all right.
（ネジ）こっちも致命傷は避けている。
Elder's wound isn't fatal either.
いったい何があったんです！？
What happened here anyway?
やられた…　ヒナタを連れ去られた。
We were attacked.
Hinata has been taken.
あっ！
なんですって！？
What?!
さらったのは　観戦に来ていた
雲隠れの忍　２人。
Two ninja from the Hidden Cloud,
who were here as spectators, took her.
この騒ぎに乗じれば→
No doubt they took advantage
of the commotion
白眼を里の外に
持ち出せると踏んだのだろう。
to take the Byakugan
out of the village.
止めようとしたんじゃが…。
I tried to stop them, but...
ネジよ…　白眼は　お前の父も
命をかけた重大な秘密。
Neji, the Byakugan is a top-secret jutsu,
which your father protected with his life.
奪われることなど
あってはならぬ！
It must not be stolen!
Go after them!
追え！　命にかえても奪還せい！
Bring it back, whatever it takes!
わかりました。
I understand.
待って　ネジ。　私も行く。
Wait, Neji!
I'm coming with you.
これは　日向の仕事だ。
This is a Hyuga matter.
だからって　１人じゃ無理よ。
But it's too much for you
to handle alone.
俺も行くぜ。　ヒナタは大事な仲間だ！
I'm coming too.
Hinata is my teammate.
それに
アンタは　ヒナタをよく思ってねえ。
Besides, you don't think
highly of Hinata.
そんなヤツが本気で
助けようとするわけねえからよ。
There's no way you'd get serious
about saving her.
アンタね！
Hey you!
ならば一緒に来い。
お前は鼻が利く。
Then come with me.
Your nose will be useful.
（テンテン）確かに追跡は
スリーマンセルのほうがやりやすいか。
I guess having a three-man cell
would make things easier for pursuit.
いや　違う。　赤丸も入れてフォーマンセル。
基本小隊だ。
No, you're wrong.
Including Akamaru, it's a four-man cell.
We're now a basic platoon.
アン！
行くぞ！
Let's go.
（木ノ葉丸）そんな動きが
あったなんて…。
I didn't know all that happened.
会場の上忍たちは
気づかなかったのかな？
Didn't the jonin in the stadium notice?
さあな。　しかし
こちらに人員を出す余裕は→
Who knows?
But they probably couldn't
spare the manpower.
なかっただろう。
なにせ　下忍のナルトたちを→
After all, the situation was
such that genin like Naruto
Ａランク任務に出さざるを
得ないような状況だったからな。
had to be dispatched on
A-rank missions.
驚いたぜ。
いきなり戦争が始まるとはな。
What a shock having a war
suddenly break out like that.
もともと忍の同盟なんぞ
あってないようなもんだ。
It's like a ninja alliance never existed.
こんなチャンス
逃す手もあるまい。
We can't let this opportunity go.
門外不出の名高き血継限界。
The celebrated Kekkei Genkai,
which is forbidden from being
taken out of the village.
木ノ葉の白眼か。
The Hidden Leaf's Byakugan.
敵は２人。
まっすぐ森を抜ける気だな。
The enemy consists of two ninja.
They intend to go straight
through the forest.
この先にあるのは
田の国との国境か。
The boundary we share with
the Land of Rice Paddies is up ahead.
最短距離で
雲隠れを目指す気ね。
They're taking the shortest route
to Hidden Cloud Village.
火の国内なら土地勘があるが→
We're familiar with areas
within the Land of Fire,
国境を越えられたらアウトだぜ。
but not beyond the border.
それまでに　けりをつけねえと。
We have to settle this
before they get there.
キューン…。
どうした？
What's the matter?
赤丸は　チャクラを嗅いだだけで
相手の力量がわかっちまう。
Akamaru can size up the enemy's strength
simply by sniffing their chakra.
敵は　かなりの手練れだそうだ。
They seem to be quite formidable.
おそらくは　中忍以上。
勝ち目はなさそうだな。
They're probably higher
than chunin level.
Our chances of victory are slim.
やりようはあるだろ！
回り込んで待ち伏せるとか。
But there are ways!
Like surrounding them and
taking them by surprise.
アン！
（キバ）おい　とまれ！
Hey stop!
どうしたの？
（ネジ）トラップか？
What is it?
A trap?
（キバ）敵のにおいで　いっぱいだぜ。
This place reeks of the enemy.
げ…。
何これ　気持悪い。
What are they? How gross.
どうやら　追跡者のチャクラに反応して
作動する仕掛けのようだ。
It seems they laid a trap that is
activated by a pursuer's chakra.
来るぞ！
Here they come!
これじゃあ　キリがないわよ。
There's no end to them.
まずいな。
トラップが発動したことで→
This is bad. Setting off the trap
may have alerted the enemy.
敵は　俺たちの追尾に
気づいた可能性がある。
クソ！　時間がねえってのに。
Damn! We're running out of time!
だったら　とれる手段はひとつね。
Then we only have one choice.
爆龍撃！
Dragon Bomb!
行って！　ここは私がやる。
だ　だが…。
Go! I'll handle this.
私なら
しばらくコイツらをとめられる。
But...
I can stop them for a while.
あの子を取り戻すんでしょ？
You're going to get her back, right?
早く！
わかった。
Hurry!
Okay!
さ～て…。
Well now...
どの武器がお好みかしら？
What weapons would
you like me to use?
かかってらっしゃい！
Come and get me!
ムチャよ！　たった１人で。
That's crazy!
All by herself?
そうだな。
だが　テンテンは→
That's true.
中・遠距離の攻撃範囲を持つ
優秀な武器使いだ。
But Tenten is a skilled weapons specialist,
capable of mid to long-range attacks.
敵を食い止め→
She had the greatest chance of stopping
the enemy, then getting out of there.
かつ　自身も逃げ切る可能性が
いちばん高かった。
時間が差し迫る中→
With time running out, we had no choice
but to have faith in her.
俺たちは
信じて託すしかなかった。
雲のヤツら
面倒なもの残しやがって。
Those damned Cloud Ninja...
Laying a nasty trap like that.
だが　あれを仕掛けるのには
それなりの時間がかかったはずだ。
However, setting up something
like that must've taken time.
ああ
トラップのにおいは　まだ新しかった。
Yeah. The scent was still fresh.
ヤツら　そう遠くには
行ってないはずだ。
They're not that far ahead.
白眼！
Byakugan.
（ネジ）見つけた。
I found them.
よし　奇襲をかけて
ヒナタを取り戻すぜ。
All right! We'll ambush them
and get Hinata back!
やめておけ。
そんな方法じゃ無理だ。
Forget it. That won't work.
じゃあ　どうするってんだ！
Then what do you suggest?!
とめてもムダだ。　俺は行くぜ。
You can't stop me. I'm going!
トラップを発動させたヤツがいるな。
Someone set off the trap.
追っ手か？
たぶんな。　急ごう。
Are they coming after us?
Probably. Let's hurry.
国境は　すぐ先だ。
ああ。
The boundary is straight up ahead.
掌底！
Right.
Palm Heel Strike!
あなたたちの
思いどおりにはなりません。
You're not going to get your way.
ムダな抵抗はよせ。
Don't try to resist.
We're in a hurry.
俺たちは急いでいる。
ゴホッ　ゴホッ。
本家の白眼なら
持ち主の生死は関係ないんだろ？
As long as a head family member
wields the Byakugan,
it doesn't matter whether
she's dead or alive, right?
このガキ。　いっそ首から
上だけ連れ帰るか。
Damn brat! How about we just
take back her head instead?
通牙！
Tunneling Fang!
なんとか間に合ったな。
キバ君。
Looks like I made it in time!
ヒナタ　逃げんぞ！
Kiba?!
Hinata! We're getting outta here!
追っ手か。
あのガキ。
- A pursuer.
- Those brats...
絶対　ぶっ殺す！
I'm gonna kill them!
そんな逃げ切れるわけないよ。
There's no way you could get away.
そのとおり。　当時の俺たちでは
実力がまるで違うからな。
You're absolutely right.
Back then we just weren't
strong enough.
下忍ごときが　ムダなあがきだ。
It's useless for a mere genin like you.
茶番に
つき合ってる暇はねえんだよ。
And we don't have time to waste!
柔拳法。
Gentle Fist...
八卦六十四掌。
8 Trigrams 64 Palms!
八卦ニ掌。
8 Trigrams 2 Palms!
四掌！　八掌！
4 Palms!
十六掌！　三十二掌！
8 Palms!
16 Palms!
六十四掌！
32 Palms!
64 Palms!
なるほど。
I see.
そうか　お前。
Now I get it.
中忍試験に出ていた日向の小僧か。
You're that Hyuga kid who was
in the Chunin Exam.
あの野郎。
That jerk.
かっこつけやがって。
Acting all tough!
フン　俺たちは
ダミーを追跡させられたわけだ。
So we were chasing a decoy.
どけ。　死とともにその力を
失うような分家の眼に用はない。
Move. We have no use for an eye
that loses its power upon death.
この先には行かせん。
I will not let you get past here.
土遁　土流波！
Earth Style: Mud Wave!
柔拳使い相手に
間合いを詰めるつもりはない。
I don't plan on letting
a Gentle Fist user come near me!
しまった！
Oh no!
土遁影分身。
《誘い込まれたか…》
Earth Style Shadow Clone?
終わりだ。
He lured me.
It's over.
手足を封じた体術使いなど。
A taijutsu user who can't use
his arms or legs...
籠の中の鳥も同然よ。
is nothing more
than a caged bird.
あれほど憎んでいたというのに。
After hating them so much,
結局　宗家の
犠牲にならねばならんとは。
you still end up being
a sacrifice for the head family.
お前も哀れな運命の持ち主だな。
What a sad destiny for you.
俺はそんなものに
殉じたんじゃない。
I didn't come reluctantly.
少なくとも今は
自分の意志でここにいる。
I'm here because I chose to!
どの道　結果は変わらない。
Whatever. The result is the same.
You will die here!
お前は　今　ここで死ぬんだ！
裂土転針！
Mud Needle!
回天！
Rotation!
遅くなったな。
ヒアシ様！
Sorry for being late.
《ヒアシ！？　日向の宗家か！》
Lord Hiashi?!
Hiashi?!
The head of the Hyuga Clan?!
八卦空掌！
8 Trigrams: Air Palm!
雑魚めが…。
ヒアシ様　なぜ　ここに！？
Pathetic.
Why are you here, Lord Hiashi?
ヒナタ様は？
What about Lady Hinata?
長老から　事の次第は聞いた。
The Elder told me the details.
ヒナタなら　今は
コウが　そばについているはずだ。
Ko should be with Hinata now.
途中で拾った
お前の仲間と一緒にな。
With your friend that
he picked up along the way.
そうですか。
しかし　この戦の折
宗家　自ら　こんな場所まで…。
I see.
But why did you leave the battlefield
to come here of all places?
ヒナタは　私の大切な娘。
Hinata is my precious daughter.
そして　お前は
大切な弟の忘れ形見だからな。
And you are the precious memento
of my late brother.
よかったわね　お互い　無事で。
Thank goodness we're all okay.
あのよ…　ネジ。
Say... Neji.
Sorry about everything.
その…　いろいろ　悪かったな。
その後　ヒナタ様誘拐を企てた
雲忍たちは拘束された。
In time, the Cloud Ninja who planned
Lady Hinata's abduction were captured.
しかし　最後に
雲の関与がなかったことから→
It turned out that the Cloud Village
was not directly involved,
国際問題には発展せず　事件は
内々に処理されたというわけだ。
so it didn't blow up into
an international incident
and we settled things internally.
木ノ葉崩しの陰で
そんな事件があったなんて…。
And that's it.
So behind the destruction
of the Hidden Leaf,
私　知らなかった。
there was an incident like that?
僕　なんか　感動しちゃったよ。
I didn't know.
That was a touching story.
それは　結構。　こちらも
話したかいがあるというものだ。
Good.
It was worth telling it to you.
ん？　ちょっと待つぞ　これ！
話って　まさか　これで全部？
Hey, wait a minute!
That's all there is to the story?
ナルト兄ちゃん
全然　関係ないぞ　これ！
But Naruto had nothing to do with this!
何を言ってる？
What are you talking about?
《俺にとって…》
ご…　ごめんなさい　ネジ兄さん。
For me...
I'm sorry, Neji.
All because of me...
わ…　私のせいで…。
顔を上げてください　ヒナタ様。
Please look up, Lady Hinata.
ヒナタ様が謝ることは
何ひとつ　ありません。
There's no reason for you
to apologize.
俺は真実を知らされず　勝手に
宗家に対し　逆恨みをしたうえで→
I thought I understood it all and bore
a grudge against the head family,
すべてを
わかったような気になっていた。
without knowing the truth.
運命なのだと　何もかも決めつけ→
I blamed fate and made myself believe
that I was the only one suffering.
自分だけが苦しんでいると
そう　思いこんでいました。
しかし　俺との戦いのなか
あの男は言いました。
But during our battle,
he told me that you were suffering
just as much as I was.
ヒナタ様も
同じように苦しんでいるんだと。
認められない自分を
どうにか変えようと→
And that you were trying so hard
to change in order to gain acceptance.
戦っているのだと。
考えたこともありませんでした。
I had never even thought about that.
俺は　自分の視野の狭さを
はっきりと教えられたんです。
He made me see how selfish
and narrow-minded I was.
ナルト君が？
うずまきナルト…
おもしろい男ですね。
Naruto did?
Naruto Uzumaki.
He's an interesting guy.
はい！
Yes!
ちゃんと　肝心なところに
絡んでるから　大丈夫だ。
He was involved in
the most important part so don't worry.
（３人）え～っ！？
お前たちの新聞
楽しみにしてるぞ。
- What?!
I'm looking forward to your article.
ちょっと　兄ちゃん
それは　ないぞ　これ！
Hey Neji, no fair!
せめて　どこが
肝心なところか　教えてくれよ！
You have to tell us what part
was important!
（ネジ）全部だよ　全部。
アイツがいなけりゃ　この話も
できなかったかもしれないからな。
It's all important. Every bit.
Without him, this story may
never have happened.
（モエギ）ナルト兄ちゃんが活躍する話が
聞きたかったのに！
We wanted to hear about
Naruto's achievements.
（ネジ）ハハハ！
俺に聞いたのが　間違いだな。
Then maybe asking me
was a mistake.
shiranai wo riyuu ni nigete bakari de
Always using "I don't care" as an excuse to run away
rakuna michi wo susumu no wakantan da yo ne
It's simpler to follow the easy path, isn't it?
demo ima dakedo kono isshu wa
But this moment right now
dare no mono demo naiyo
Belongs to no one
what's going on, what's going on
chiisai koroni egai teta
In order to become the person
nari tai jibun ni naru tameni
I wanted to be when I was little
nani shite nani wo mirebaii notte
What should I do? What should I see?
mayocchi yau toki mo aru yo ne dakedo
Sometimes I'm confused, but...
(anytime) kitto ima daijina mono
(Anytime) What's really important now
(anytime) sore ha koko ni aru kara
(Anytime) ...is right here with us
(anytime) kowagaranai de sono mama
(Anytime) So don't be afraid
ikou shinjite
And just go, Believe
shiranai wo riyuu ni nigete bakari de
Always using "I don't care" as an excuse to run away
rakuna michi wo susumu no wakantan da yo ne
It's simpler to follow the easy path, isn't it?
demo ima dakedo kono isshu wa
But this moment right now
dare no mono demo naiyo
Belongs to no one
what's going on, what's going on
hey, hey, hey I think u can do it !
yoku mimi wo sumasete kimi wo yobu hou e
Listen closely and follow the voice that's calling you
hiru no aida no aida made sagashi temite yo
Look carefully between the buildings
mitsukaru yo kitto
I'm sure you'll find it
jibun wo ugokasu nanika
The thing that moves you
Next Episode
W-Who the hell are you, Old man?!
You scared me!
You're the one who scared me
with your loud scream!
Hey, wait a minute.
What're you doing in my house?
I don't know.
Before I knew it, I was standing here.
"Before you knew it"?
What kind of stupid joke is...
Mister?
C-Could you take a look
at the mirror?!
Next time on Naruto Shippuden: "The Man Who Died Twice"
The Man Who Died Twice
G-G-Ghost!